<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some few considerations propounded, as so many scruples by Mr. Henry Robinson in a letter to Mr. Iohn Dury upon his epistolary discourse: with Mr. Duryes answer thereunto. VVherein is observable with what overtures of spirit they endeavour to edifie each other, not withstanding their differing judgements and opinions about the Independent and Presbyterian way. Published by a well-willer to peace and truth, in expectation that it may no little conduce, either to the reconciling of such controversies, or to the debating them with lesse noise and bitternesse. Whereunto is annexed another epistolary discourse, written by Mr. John Dury, to a worthy knight, concerning the principles of meditation: from which rules may be gathered to direct men to order their thoughts, so as to finde a resolution of all their doubts.</title>
            <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E345_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200979</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861578</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861578</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113716</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113716)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E345[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some few considerations propounded, as so many scruples by Mr. Henry Robinson in a letter to Mr. Iohn Dury upon his epistolary discourse: with Mr. Duryes answer thereunto. VVherein is observable with what overtures of spirit they endeavour to edifie each other, not withstanding their differing judgements and opinions about the Independent and Presbyterian way. Published by a well-willer to peace and truth, in expectation that it may no little conduce, either to the reconciling of such controversies, or to the debating them with lesse noise and bitternesse. Whereunto is annexed another epistolary discourse, written by Mr. John Dury, to a worthy knight, concerning the principles of meditation: from which rules may be gathered to direct men to order their thoughts, so as to finde a resolution of all their doubts.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
                  <author>Well-Willer to Peace and Truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Green, and are to be sold at his shop in Ivie Lane, at the signe of the Gun.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 18th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664? --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dury, John, 1596-1680 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113716:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113716:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME FEW CONSIDERATIONS PROPOVNDED, As ſo many Scruples by Mr. <hi>Henry Robinſon</hi> in a Letter to Mr. <hi>Iohn Dury</hi> upon his Epiſtolary Diſcourſe: With Mr. <hi>Duryes</hi> Anſwer thereunto.</p>
            <p>VVherein is obſervable with what overtures of ſpirit they endeavour to edifie each other, notwithſtanding their differing Judgements and Opinions about the Independent and Presbyterian way.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by a Well-willer to Peace and Truth, in expectation that it may no little conduce, either to the reconciling of ſuch Controverſies, or to the debating them with leſſe noiſe and bitterneſſe.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed another Epiſtolary Diſcourſe, written by Mr. <hi>John Dury,</hi> to a worthy Knight, concerning the Principles of Meditation: From which Rules may be gathered to direct men to order their thoughts, ſo as to finde a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of all their doubts.</p>
            <bibl>2 Tim. 2. 24, 25.</bibl>
            <q>A ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient, in meekneſſe inſtructing (even) thoſe that oppoſe themſelves.</q>
            <bibl>Gal. 6. 1, 2.</bibl>
            <q>If a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpirituall reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of weekneſſe, conſidering thy ſelf leſt thou alſo be tempted.</q>
            <bibl>Pſal. 50. v. 23.</bibl>
            <q>Who ſo offereth praiſe glorifieth me, and to him that ordereth his Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aright, will I ſhew the ſalvation of God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Green,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Ivie Lane,</hi> at the ſigne of the Gun. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113716:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113716:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend and much honoured, Mr. IOHN DURY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to that ſmall talent of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which it pleaſed the eternall Diſpencer, from whom all good gifts proceed, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon me: I may ſafely ſay, and that with great joy of heart; how amongſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as doe argue, and debate the preſent diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of the Churches, particularly about the Independent and Presbyteriall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I have not met with any who ever yet expreſſed ſo ſweet, ſo brotherly, ſo Chriſtian, and even ſo Apoſtolicall a ſpirit, as without any other proſpective, I clearly ſee inhabiting in you breaſt, by ſome letters which came forth about two months agoe, entituled, An Epiſtolary Diſcourſe, &amp;c. with others, which it pleaſed my worthy friend Mr. Hartlib to favour me withall: your proceeding with the Apologiſts therein, I cannot better expreſſe, then, as if it were between your own right hand and your left; towards which, any other then an equall proportion of liberty and affection would bee both unnaturall and unjuſt.</p>
            <p>It is now eight monthes ſince I was bold to enquire after you in hope you had been in England, with an intention of importuning you (which ſince I perceived to be needleſſe through your own for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe) to engage your ſelfe towards the reconciling of this Clergie War; but underſtanding you were ſo farre off, and withall ſcarce ſetled, or well at leaſure, I forbore purpoſely to give you farther trouble. However becauſe in the beginning of your Letter to Mr. Hartlib, as alſo in the other to Mr. Good win and Mr. Nye: you
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113716:3"/>
ſeemed deſirous of a further correſpondency with the Apologiſts, or ſome others in their way; whereby you might have knowne the ſtate of their caſe in England: and as I conceive would gladly for the common Cauſe ſake, that ſome punctuall anſwer were made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Epiſtolary Diſcourſe, which I am fearfull will not ſucceed as yet, in that I apprehend that moſt men of their way, are rather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally poſſeſſed and taken up with an imminent danger, and daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting ſome ſudden ſentence of abſolute ſilence or certaine baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for what is ſaid already, through a moſt fierce perſecution of certaine unquiet Presbyterian Spirits: the conſideration whereof, as alſo the great deſire I have of being farther knowne unto you in the high eſteem of thoſe admirble gifts which God hath given you, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with mee to trouble you with theſe few generall conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, upon the reading of your Epiſtolary Diſcourſe; whereby you will perceive I take not upon me neither to ſtate the controverſie (ſo much above my ſlender abilities) and yet not as one altogether without hopes, through Gods mercy (which is ſtill moſt eminent when moſt rely'd upon) and the love you beare to truth (a greater then which I know not where to find to make an enſample unto my ſelfe) but that they may in ſome ſmall manner, and by degrees bee conducing unto the publique good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. Brieſly then about the middle of your book; you pleaſe to ſay the Apologiſts are not to be tolerated unleſſe they can ſhew their way of Non-communion to be the only way of God; and the Presbyteriall contrary &amp;c. But I ſhould ſuppoſe it ſufficient, if they can prove their way to be one of the wayes of God, if but a poſſibility of ſalvation in their way; ſince they profeſſe before God and man, and muſt be beleeved in charity, that they cannot comply with a good conſcience in any other way: our Saviours Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of: He that was not againſt him was on his part, Mark. 9. 40. ſeems to make not a little to this purpoſe; and ſo much the rather, they may be tolerated, whilſt they inſiſt not ſo much that the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall government ſhould be rejected by the State, as that their own way be barely ſuffered among themſelves: but whilſt the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian party (or ſuch as will not permit a Civil abode but) baniſh or exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll all ſuch as differing in opinon doe ſeparate themſelves from Church ſociety; they are Authors of a more deſperate ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113716:3"/>
far worſe then non-communion, or the ſeparatiſts themſelves in whatſoever ſenſe, becauſe they take away all poſſibility of regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, if they were in an error by their converſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 21. The leſſe the cauſe of ſeparation is; the greater the fault is, in thoſe that make it:</p>
            <p>The cauſe of ſeparation is great in apprehenſion of the Apologiſts, but leſſe in judgement of the Presbyterians, proceeding only, as theſe uſually alledge, about things indifferent; and therefore they ought the rather to give way unto them, ſince they may contrive it with a quiet conſcience; all the reaſon they give unto the contrary, is the goodlineſſe of uniformity in the outward comlineſſe, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſtood upon as neceſſary; much leſſe to be preſſed ſo far, as not to ſuffer ſuch to live amongſt them, who cannot comply through tenderneſſe of conſcience; godly, reaſonable, and underſtanding men, as they are thought to be, ſhould not by charitable men, be deemed to ſeparate to their ſo great inconveniences, if their conſcience could otherwiſe diſpence with them; whereas the Presbyterians here, which ſtand upon their pantofles, enjoying all acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modations, may eaſier be ſuppoſed to keep their diſpiſed brethren of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent way to ſuch hard taske and meaſure, to gratifie their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 23. Let us remember, that the ſervants of God muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle to all men; chiefly unto our neereſt brethren. If the Apologiſts can be thought to ſtrive, 'tis only in a defenſive way, to keep their conſciences from being raviſhed into a unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; whereof they finde themſelves not able to give an account neither to God nor man; but they are the Presbyterians, which may be ſaid, both properly and actually to ſtrive, and that with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall civill weapons, whileſt by their doctrine, inſtigation, or appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, their poor brethren, which cannot with a good conſcience comply with them, are perſecuted by diſcountenancing, turning out of their Miniſtery and livelihoods, impriſoning and baniſhing, through grief and manifold inconveniences, even unto death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 24. You ſay, if ſpirituall relation cannot be ſetled by the wiſdome and loving affections of ſpirituall office-bearers within the Church amongſt themſelves, then it is juſt that they ſhould forfeit their ſpirituall right and liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113716:4"/>If this be ſo; I would gladly ſee it proved from evidence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or good reaſon; for, I conccive, that as Chriſt did only pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe for us our Chriſtian rights and liberties: ſo no State or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, no body but himſelf may take upon him to abridge us of them: Secondly, that no civill miſdemeanors can be juſt cauſe to abridge us of our Chriſtian liberty: Thirdly, that diviſions in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about a Church-way do not neceſſarily conclude diviſions in a State: And laſtly, ſuch as do actually diſturb the civill State, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like peace, both ought, and may be puniſhed, even unto death, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abridging ſuch offenders; much leſſe the civilly innocent in their ſpirituall rights and liberties. The utmoſt extent and height of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians differing in opinion, which I ever heard of, was this. Firſt, that they might have leave to ſearch the Scriptures: Secondly, to try the ſpirits, examine the doctrines which were taught them, and ſo rejecting error, hold faſt the truth; worſhpping God in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he requires, with confirming and edifying one another in all piety and godlineſſe, for diſcharging of a good conſcience, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and man. If it be objected, that men may not worſhip God after a falſe manner, under pretence of a true one; nor pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh errors in ſtead of truth: I anſwer, that nothing can be ſaving truth, nor any kind of worſhipping God prove acceptable from any man, which is not held to be ſuch in his own conſcience and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. I ſubmit my ſelf to heare, reade, or be informed in whatſoever ſhall be required of me; and it may on ſtrong preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be conceived, that the ſundry diſadvantages I lie under, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, with the many benefits I might receive by conforming, do make me no little willing and deſirous, that my very judgement and conſcience could be brought about to approve and agree in what the State eſtabliſheth, ſo it might be with a good conſcience towards God and man; but if after all this I ſhall profeſſe in preſence of the Lord, that I do not finde evidence by all that was alledged, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing of my conſcience, I deſire to ſee cleer grounds from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, on which any politick ends of State may any wayes proceed to offer violence, or any degree of compulſive means to work upon my conſcience and underſtanding, on which ſuch ſpirituall as have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been uſed were not able to prevail, ſince ſuch only we finde warrantable and ſanctified in Scripture to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113716:4"/>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. They ſhould be ſo tolerated, as may be no prejudice to that Church whereof the State it ſelf is profeſſedly a nurſing mother.</p>
            <p>I cannot apprehend how the ſimilitude can hold between a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtian and a publike State in many reſpects; I will urge on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in one, <hi>viz.</hi> a publike State may at ſometime, both have, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thwarting, croſſe or contrary opinions to be believed, and yet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, though (if it were granted) not ſo peacebly, not ſo ſecutely as is objected. But a private Chriſtian cannot poſſibly, at one and the ſame time, believe two diametrically oppoſite opinions to be true in the ſelf ſame reſpect.</p>
            <p>I wiſh you would be pleaſed to ſtate the courſe and orderly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference you ſpeak of, <hi>p.</hi> 26. which doubtleſſe all Independents will with you approve of.</p>
            <p>I do not find it expreſſed in Scripture, that Chriſtian Magiſtrates have any thing to do in ſetting up an outward viſible worſhip under the Goſpell; or that they can any wayes be furthering of it, except by giving good example unto others, as being members of the Church, or in protecting the Saints, whileſt they apply themſelves to worſhip God, according to the integrity of their own conſciences, in ſpirit and in truth, for ſince the Magiſtrates weapons are coercive, teriall, camall, if they take upon them the vindication of ſpirituall neglect or defect, each State ſetting up its own, a different worſhip; men muſt from time to time take that to be the trueſt, and ſubject their conſciences to that which hath the ſharpeſt ſword to fight for it, ſtill changing Religion according to the event of warre; with the ſundry alterations of States and Kingdomes. And though I am not well ſatisfied with the expreſſion you uſe concerning the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a State: I ſuppoſe you will ſufficiently apprehend me, if I querie, whether the conſcience of every State, can be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and at the day of judgement excuſe all ſuch as have been caſt away through falſe worſhips, which they ſet up in relation to their own conſciences reſpectively, compelling the people to ſubmit thereto? If not, I querie again, if it be not are argument of greateſt indiſcretion, for reaſonable men and women to reſigne up their own underſtandings, unto ſuch as cannot bear them harmleſſe for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of greateſt preſumption and tyrannie in thoſe who aſſume unto themſelves a ſpirituall dominion over others, whom they can
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113716:5"/>
neither give a ſpirituall aſſurance to at preſent; nor provide for them if need be a ſpirituall deliverance hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 28. You ſay the Civill Magiſtrate may not meddle with what is ſpirituall, nor the Spirituall office bearer with what is Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, which I grant: and yet <hi>p.</hi> 29. you ſay the Civill Magiſtrate muſt have the cognizance of the juſt and orderly behaviour of thoſe which doe adminiſter Spirituall ordinances: wherein I beſeech you, conſider whether this be not a direct way of ſetting the Civill and Spirituall office bearers at odds amongſt themſelves; as put the caſe the Civill Magiſtrate tells the Spirituall, that he hath not well &amp; orderly adminiſtred the Ordinances, admoniſhes him to reforme; and upon reſuſall proceeds to puniſh him: on the contrary, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Magiſtrate juſtifies himſelfe; flyes to his Spirituall weapons in his owne defence, and if they prevail not, in likelihood endeavours to ſtir up the people againſt the Civill Magiſtrate; and how you can avoid this great diſturbance upon theſe grounds I cannot poſſibly imagine, but much deſire to be informed thereof, if your leaſure may permit, and that upon further thoughts you continue of the ſame opinion. You make it likewiſe within the ſphere of the Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to keep people from chooſing Teachers according to their owne humours, their owne underſtandings, and Teachers from drawing people after them: how is this I beſeech you, conſiſtent with the liberty? nay the charge which is impoſed upon Chriſtians for trying of the ſpirits, and holding faſt that which is good: if they may not heare ſuch as they apprehend to be ſent from Chriſt, and imbrace ſuch doctrines as they take to be ſaving truths, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to their ſalvation according to that light of reaſon and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the Scriptures, which God hath given them for this very purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 36. <q>If thoſe you call common principles (whilſt you ſay the Apologiſts inſiſting on generalities, cannot be brought to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) were demonſtrative, as you alleadge the Scriptures may bee demonſtratively analized. <hi>P.</hi> 4. I ſhould thinke it the worke of ſome Angell to have it once effected; and as well the Apologiſts as all others who now differ in opinion, would quickly grow toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into an unity of faith:</q> But till then I ſhall expect, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures, there will be hereſies, and in the mean time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113716:5"/>
conceive that nothing, except this demonſtrative analizing ſacred truth, will ſooner vanquiſh them, then the ſuffering them, to bee with all poſſible freedome examined and debated, which muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily infer the moſt acknowledged truths themſelves, to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſame proceeding, in that what one man, Church or Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on takes to be truth, another perhaps accounts no leſſe then hereſie: And if Paul told the Galathians, that if a good Angell, an Angell from heaven, ſhould preach any other Goſpell to them then what the Apoſtles had done before, he ſhould be accurſed: I conceive we may much more try the ſpirits of mortall men, of like paſſions and infirmities with our ſelves, conſequently holding faſt what wee finde ſound, and rejecting what appeares to bee erronious by the touchſtone of holy Writ, according to our owne reaſon, underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and faith: ſince we neither may or can judge truly of them (no more then ſee with the eyes of other men) by the reaſon, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and faith of others: neither can I apprehend a third or any meane betwixt theſe two conditions.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Pag.</hi> 30. I conſeſſe a diſſolved government, may often times prove dangerous and fatail to any State, both Civill and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; and yet not ſo dangerous not fatall as a dominiering, over rigid, tyrannicall government, eſpecially in the ſpirituall ſtate; and both of them are therefore to be regulated according to their bounds and rules: If Church diſcipline and cenſures will not prevaile on Church members, I finde no warrant to flye to Civill, but conceive it highly condemned even by that place of Paul, where he blames the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians for going to law with one another, and that before unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; beſides all Civill ſtates account themſelves in a manner perfect for their civill condition and conſtitution: As firſt, they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in Lawes, they have as many as they will themſelves, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to underſtand them fully, even to the leaſt jot, and every man is bound to know them exactly, and keep them in the letter. But for ſpirituall matters we know but in part; and therefore ought to reach forth to what is wanting, not refuſing to lend an eare unto it, though tendered by a ſtammering illiterate tongue of ſome other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſpiſed ſoule: As all truth for the moſt part, even from the beginning hath been diſcountenanced, and rejected upon the firſt diſcovery, and ſo much the rather in that the Primitive Chriſtians
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113716:6"/>
however weak and ignorant in faith and knowledge, the Apoſtles found them; yet had they ſuch amongſt them in both reſpects, as far exceeded all others ever ſince; neither have we ſuch infallible teachers like theirs, to confirm unto us what we have for truth, or adde unto us what is wanting.</p>
            <p>To <hi>pag.</hi> 31. I muſt needs confeſſe, the opinion of a greater light is no little deceitfull; but doth not God require that we ſhould walk according to ſuch appearing light, whether true or falſe, I muſt be guided by it, as it appears unto my ſelfe? and how can God be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with me for ſerving him to my power? or how can man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne me for differing from him, when I have uſed all ſuch rationall common principles which he could preſcribe to bring me to be of this opinion, without prevailing upon my conſcience? You ſay well with the Apoſtle, that if any man thinketh he knoweth any thing he knoweth nothing, yet as he ought to know, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 2. and yet a man muſt be ruled by that which he thus but thinks to know: ſo, much leſſe ground hath any man to impoſe what he knowes not, (for even his knowledge neither is no better) upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who knowing nothing, yet knowes as much as himſelf: Nay, a Synod, Councel, or State, have ſo little preemimence in this reſpect, as that we muſt not look upon them with reſpect of perſons, unleſſe we will juſtifie the Church of Rome in their implicit faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 32. You approve the caſting off ſubjection and abſolute obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto Epiſcopacy, but would not have diſſolved the brotherly correſponcie in a Presbyterie; and certainly it ſhould not be, but it muſt then continue brotherly; we muſt run hand in hand like bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo long as we can keep a good conſcience both towards God and man; and if afterwards upon juſt grounds in our opinions, for ſome reſpects, we are forced to ſeparate from them, we ſhall be yet deſirous to reſt among them, that if poſſibly they may be won by a godly converſation; but if like a curſt father, or imperious Maſter, they endeavour with rods and ſtaves to drive us from our Father and Maſter, which is in heaven; or from our native countrey, friends and livelihoods, they do not only ceaſe to be brotherly, but caſt away all hopes or poſſibility of reclaiming us if we were in an error.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pap.</hi> 34. You make duties of practice no leſſe fundamentall in the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, then the knowledge of neceſſary
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113716:6"/>
truths, according unto which principle, I ſuppoſe the Apologiſts ought to be permitted, both to practiſe ſuch duties as they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend requiſite, and not to joyn with ſuch as they eſteem ſuperfluous, erroneous, ſince both may be no leſſe of faith, then for one that eateth, and another that eateth not, whileſt both give thanks to God, as Paul ſayes of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 6.</p>
            <p>To <hi>pag.</hi> 37. As they will not refuſe ſubjection to their own Paſtor, that hath the charge of their ſouls, ſo much leſſe when what he requires of them be confirmed by the approbation of a Presbyterie, other Churches, or Brethren; but this muſt be in ſuch things as they may yeeld unto with a good conſcience; and in caſe they finde reaſon for diſſenting, they are liable only to be cenſured by their own Church, which hath power over them, not by any others, who have no juriſdiction, much leſſe authoritative o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſative: Synods and Aſſemblies may well be convocated, and take counſel, debate, and ſeek to vanquiſh ſuch difficulties as ariſe without a Majeſteriall juriſdiction, which neither our Saviour or his Apoſtles did ever make uſe of, or give command to others to practiſe it in after ages; Chriſts kingdome was not of this world, his body is myſticall; and ſuch means only are capable to build us up therein.</p>
            <p>Thus have I preſumed in as weak as curſory a manner to weigh the foregoing paſſages of your Epiſtolary diſcourſe, in the unequall ballance, like enough, of my own underſtanding, but proceeding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely from a deſire of being better informed in what I am at a loſſe: I doubt not but your ſingular candidneſſe of mind will make a good interpretation of it.</p>
            <p>The ſetling of an Eccleſiaſticall Peace, I apprehend to be of ſuch eminent weight and conſideration, as that without it Chriſtians will never in any comparative degree be brought to unity in diſcipline and doctrine; and that more ſouls are kept from knowledge of the truth, and miſcarry through perſecuting one another, for cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſcience, then by reaſon of all other ſuch great differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, whether for diſcipline or doctrine.</p>
            <p>If you have pupliſhed any of your other thoughts, concerning this ſubject beſides your <hi>Conſultatio Theologie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. Letter to the L. Forbes, and your <hi>Informati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſiis Reformatis oblata,</hi> &amp;c. I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113716:7"/>
ſhould excedingly rejoyce to have a ſight thereof; <q>and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially touching the demonſtrative analizing the Scriptures, which I conceive would be a greater Jewell, then all that ever Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wrote of, from the Cedar to the ſhrub:</q> Wherefore I moſt humbly beſeech you, for the publike good, that you would not ſuffer the leaſt dram of your Meditations in this behalfe, any longer to lie waſte or dormant, which, though it were not yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and compleat, might by degrees, and contemplations of others well-affected, be further improved, to the eternall honour of the Almighty, to whoſe gracious protection, I cordially recommend your moſt pious endeavous, and to them moſt earneſtly deſiring to become any wayes ſubſervient, do in all humble manner remain</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>the 5. of <hi>November,</hi> 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt devoted Friend and Servant in the Lord,
Henry Robinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113716:7"/>
            <head>To his much reſpected and loving friend in Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Henry Robinſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough your Letter did miſcarry, and never came in the Originall to my hand; nor the Copy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of till I was reſolving to goe from Rotterdam to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards England, yet I thought my ſelfe obliged to anſwer your love; which then I did beginne to do, but was interrupted in the proſecution hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: nevertheleſſe leſt either mine owne purpoſe or your equitable deſires ſhould be fruſtrate; or I ſeem careleſſe to give you ſome ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to your ſcruples; I ſhall now endeavour to perfect the thoughts which once were in my minde, beſeeching the Lord to aſſiſt us both with the encreaſe of his Grace; that in this and all other ſervices his Glory may be advanced by us.</p>
            <p>But before I enter upon the matter, I muſt truly tell you, That as I cannot acknowledge any of theſe things in my ſelfe which you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute unto me beyond my meaſure; ſo I muſt needs take notice of the large expreſſion of your affections which I am bound to requite and entertaine; not only becauſe you have moderate and ſober thoughts of your ſelf, and becauſe your way ſeems to me very inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous, and your whole ſtrain conſcionable in the doubts which you make; all which deſerves reſpect: but chiefly becauſe the duty of Chriſtian love (even towards thoſe that deſerve it not) is the only meanes of edification towards them: For it doth make the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of divine Truth in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereof without offence: and therefore fit to be received through Gods bleſſing with profit by them to whom it is offered. For as God is moved, and is powerfull
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113716:8"/>
only by his love to reveale himſelfe to us, offering himſelfe as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſpirits to his children, which are our ſoules; ſo we as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch a Father are bound to doe all things in his love; for ſo we are commanded by the Apoſtle, Epheſ. 5. 1, 2. and towards our Brethren we ſhould as members of each other advance that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which we have of him and his truth in love only and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: For what we doe with any other affection is done in our owneſtrength, and will be found either ineffectuall, or hurtfull to edification. Therefore as I make no doubt but you have ſpoken the truth from your heart: ſo I ſhall aſſure you that I ſhall without partiality lay open unto you my thoughts, and hold out the light which I have received; not only in theſe things which you have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but in all other matters wherein I ſhall finde my ſelfe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to beare witneſſe to the Truth.</p>
            <p>Now then beſeeching him againe to direct our thoughts, and guide our ſpirits in all truth by his holy Spirit of promiſe in Jeſus Chriſt, to be able to doe all things unblameably to the glory of his Grace and our mutuall comfort, I ſhall endeavour to reſolve the doubts which you propoſe, and give you as briefly as may bee the beſt ſatisfaction I can.</p>
            <p>1. To the firſt Scruple then out of pag. 20. concerning the tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apologiſts: I finde that you take not up rightly my meaning; I will therefore explaine it firſt more fully, and then come to the particulars of your exception. Conſider therefore that in the whole firſt part of my Diſcourſe, and conſequently in that place which you alleadge, I ſpeake not of a Toleration of Forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance whereby one Chriſtian is bound with all long ſuffering to ſupport another in meekneſſe: nor of a Toleration of Connivence in a Civill ſtate, whereby the Magiſtrate may winke at things which he cannot mend, when they are not ſetled according to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but I doe ſpeake of that Toleration which I ſuppoſed the Apologiſts did ſue for; which I muſt call a Toleration of Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the Magiſtrate as the publicke Miniſter of God, in the viſible ſociety of men ſhould ſetle therein for the welfare thereof. My Queſtion then in the firſt part of the Diſcourſe is not, what in State Policie (I ſhould have ſaid humane Prudencie) a Magiſtrate may doe lawfully, if his inclination leads him thereunto: or what
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113716:8"/>
in charity as a Chriſtian he ſhould intend to doe privately: but what in ſtate wiſdome as it is ſubordinate unto Gods will in the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtianity is moſt expedient for him to doe in his publicke place. And in this reſpect I ſay, that I thinke it no wiſdome in a ſtate ſeeking a Reformation of Religion, to tolerate by way of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation (that is in effect to authoriſe and ſetle for a time) a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke profeſſion, which they cannot finde to bee the true and only way which God alloweth. This is the meaning of my aſſertion in the whole firſt part of my Diſcourſe: and in this ſenſe only I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the ſtate to grant the Apologiſts their Petition: but if for other more important reaſons it cannot be denyed, then I thought it would be wiſdome in the ſtate, ſo to limitate the Toleration which they ſhould grant for time and manner; that thereby a full agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and unity might be brought to paſſe between the Apologiſts and their Brethren, which is the ſubject of the two following heads of my Diſcourſe: and I am ſtill in the ſame minde which then I was in.</p>
            <p>But if you or any make a doubt of the firſt Poſition, take notice of the grounds whereupon I raiſe it; and if you or any, can ſhew me that they are not ſound, I ſhall quit them with their conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
            <p>I conceive then the Magiſtrate to be Gods Vicegerent, over the ſociety of men, as it is a Civill Body; and that his charge is to looke to the Naturall conſtitution and viſible face of that ſociety, to keep it in a frame ſubordinate unto the glory of God; that it may appeare that God by him ruleth in the world in the Kingdome of men. Hee then is bound as a Vicegerent of the moſt High to authorize (that is to ſet up in the name of his Sovereign) nothing but that which his beſt underſtanding tells him, is the will of his Sovereigne: Now he cannot be ignorant of this; that his true worſhip ſhould only be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed in his name, becauſe that is only according to his will. Therefore I conclude that it will be no wiſdome in him to authoriſe the practiſe of any Religion in the ſtate, committed by God unto his inſpection, but that which he knoweth to be the true worſhip of God; and if he knoweth it not to be the true way of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, He hath no warrant to authoriſe it. He may (if he cannot avoid the Toleration) doe, as God doth with us; winke at it, untill the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113716:9"/>
time of reformation, which is in his eye; and in the mean time, direct all unto the beſt ends he can, in hope of redreſſe, but may not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and ſettle what his Soveraign doth not allow in his worſhip: This is my ground for the duty of the Magiſtrate: as for that which I call the only way of God, which the Magiſtrate is to look to, I conceive it to be nothing elſe but the true way, which God doth intend ſhould be obſerved for his glory: For I conceive that his true way is but one only way, for God is but one only God, and his name is one: The way of his glory muſt be therefore as his name is one only way, becauſe his glory is nothing elſe but the manifeſtation of his name, from all which, I ſuppoſe, I may lawfully inferre thus much, except the Apologiſts can ſhew that their way of non-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is the only way of God; that it will be no wiſdome in the ſtate to authorize it joyntly with the way which they have ſetled, and acknoleged to be the true way; for this were to make the name of God, which he in his Vicegerency is to uphold, which is but one in glory, manifold, againſt the intention of God in Chriſt, and the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Vicegerency: For if God doth manifeſtly declare that all Chriſtians are called in Chriſt to partake of his glory, by being one<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> body and one ſpirit in him, as partaking of one Baptiſme, of one faith, and of one hope of their calling throuhg him, then it is alſo manifeſt that his Vicegerent on earth amongſt men, ſhould advance by all lawfull means which belong outwardly to the ſphere of his charge, tho ſetlement of this unity, to be as viſible as may be amongſt thoſe who make profeſſion to anſwer the calling of God in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
            <p>From all which I ſuppoſe you may gather an anſwer to your ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals: For when you ſay, to obtain a toleration, it is ſufficient, if they can prove their way to be one of the wayes of God, if but a poſſibility of ſalvation therein: I anſwer that I ſee not how Gods wayes to ſalvation can be ſaid to be many, Chriſt Jeſus is but one yeſterday, to day and for ever the ſame, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 8. and without him there is no ſalvation. Now his way to ſave, is but one, which is by faith; and the means to beget faith is but one: this is the word, and the way to bring the faithfull by this means to the Father is but one: namely, the government and leading of the Spirit, which directeth the children of God in all truth anſwerable to, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113716:9"/>
diſcernable by the tenor of his covenant with them in the Word. If then the Word be but one, the covenant in it one, the truth in the Spirit but one; and the government of ſouls to enjoy God it that truth through the Spirit be alſo but one; I know not what you mean by the many wayes of God, and thoſe having a poſſibility of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; except you mean the manifold degrees of the revelation to, and of the apprehenſion of that one way, in ſeverall perſons, which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry improperly called the way of God. So then, when you ſay one of the wayes of God, wherein is a poſſibility of ſalvation: If I ſhould take your words in the beſt ſenſe that I can give them, I muſt underſtand them to be ſpoken of any one degree of the knowledge of Gods wayes which may be effectuall to work ſalvation by Gods bleſſing, and in this ſenſe I agree with you, that all ſuch as are come to any degree of ſaving knowledge, ought to be permitted to walk in that light which they have, and ought not to be conſtrained againſt their conſcience, to follow a practice wherein they ſee no light: But although from hence it followeth, that they ought to be born withall, as profeſſors of Chriſtiany in ſuch or ſuch a growth, yet it doth not follow, that it would be wiſdome in a State to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize their way by an act of publike toleration, whereby they ſhould be ſtinted to that degree of growth in the profeſſion of the Goſpel, when the State doth not know that to be the true Way which God doth intend and allow, to bring all to the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, anſwerable to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt. For, ſeeing God hath revealed, that the gifts which he hath given by his Spirit unto his Miniſters, are given for the perfecting of the Saints, and the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till they be brought unto this degree of growth, in a manly ſtature, that they may not alwayes be in a childiſh condition of doubtfulneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> tainty, to be toſſed too and fro, and carryed about with every<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> blaſt of doctrine, which cunning men, for their own ends, will<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 12. 17.</note> craftily inſinuate, lying in wait to deceive unſtable ſouls: ſeeing (I ſay) God hath revealed this to be his intention, and hath ſhewed to his Saints the way by which it will be brought to paſſe: namely, by this only way that they ſhould deal truly, without deceit, by word or deed, one with another in love, by which they ſhould be able to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113716:10"/>
grow up in all things into him, which is the head even Chriſt Jeſus: and to the end that this their true dealing may work out this growth in them effectually, and prevent the cunning craftineſſe of men who lye in wait to deceive, ſeeing hee hath ſhewed them that they ought all to be ſetled together in one body under their only head: and bee fitly joyned together, and compacted in one ſociety; that by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall joynts and ligatures which his Spirit through love in the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall care of each other doth frame amongſt them, they may make the increaſe of the body, in the meaſure of every part, by that which every joynt ſupplyeth unto the edifying of themſelves in their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of love: ſeeing (I ſay againe) all this is thus by God declared, therefore it followeth; that not only the whole body of Beleevers in a Nation, may by a right from God compact themſelves together, by their joynts and ligatures for their mutuall ſtrengthning in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall duties, to doe all things as one man in Chriſt; but they ought to depend in this relation only from Chriſt as their head, and act to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards each other only by the ability which he giveth: And Chriſts Vicegerent on earth, appointed for the inſpection of Civill and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward matters, muſt not preſume either to hinder them in the uſe of theſe meanes of their ſpirituall growth unto the ſtature of a perfect man within themſelves; or injoyne them to act only, as from and under his Authority that which is to be done in this kinde. For this cauſe we ſay, that the Magiſtrates ſanction in ſpirituall matters of edification for the execution of duties and compacting of the Body; is but <hi>de bene eſſe, &amp; cumulativè</hi> requiſite for outward protection, and not at all neceſſary for to give a being unto the worke it ſelfe: nor is it from his Civill ſanction, that the whole Body of Beleevers in a Nation is made one; but they are bound for their owne growth and preſervation to make themſelves one, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt: nor may the Vicegerent of Chriſt on earth (if he will not incurre the high diſpleaſure of his ſovereign) abſtruct this growth of Chriſts ſpirituall Body, but is bound to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it by all the aſſiſtance that he can contribute thereunto, and ought to take away the lets which may hinder it, wherof this would be a maine one, to authoriſe ſeverall wayes, and allow them as waies of God, to conſtitute the Body of Chriſt, and manifeſt the truth of his worſhip; when hee cannot be ignorant that there is but one
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113716:10"/>
way agreeable to the will of God in doing this.</p>
            <p>As touching the place Mark. 9. 20. which you alleadge, <hi>He that is not againſt us is on our part:</hi> doth inferre to me thus much only; that private men<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought not to be prohibited to make uſe of the name of Chriſt, or to walke in a way not oppoſite to Chriſt, although they joyne not themſelves to follow Chriſt with his true Diſciples. For the queſtion is there, of hindring ſome (who followed not Chriſt as the Apoſtles did) to make uſe of his name to doe miracles; Chriſt forbids his Diſciples to hinder ſuch, from doing what they did, by a rule of Prudencie, that ſuch could not lightly ſpeake evill of him. This caſe doth hold well amongſt private Chriſtians in the way of mutuall edification: but it doth not reach the point which I inſiſt upon in reſpect of the duty of a ſtate. For there is a vaſt diſtance between the duty of a Diſciple of Chriſt in not hindring particular mens practiſes, which hurt not their wayes in Chriſtianity, and the granting of a Toleration by a Magiſtrate to an Aſſembly or many Aſſemblies of men to practice publickly in the ſtate that which hee doth not finde to be the true way of God. This difference is great many wayes, but particularly in this, that ſuch a granting of a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, is an act of publicke Approbation, which to declare is not alwayes wiſdome in a private Chriſtian, far leſſe in a ſtate. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to hinder in that caſe is one thing, and to give a Toleration in this, is quite another matter.</p>
            <p>As for the charge laid upon the Presbyteriall Brethren in the end of this Paragraphe, that they will not ſuffer any Civill abode to any, that differ in opinion, ſeparate from Church ſociety from them; I know not how you can make it good; nor will I beleeve it, without ſufficient proof; nor ought you to alleadge it without a ſure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted warrant; therefore as a thing ſpoken in haſte and out of too much jealouſie, I will leave it till God let you ſee the contrary in their unblameable wayes of converſation to gaine all men, by lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forbearance with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Pag.</hi> 21. Upon the words, <hi>The leſſe the cauſe of ſeparation is, the greater the fault is in thoſe that make it,</hi> you make no exception: but you apply the Aſſertion againſt the Presbyterian Brethren, for the advantage of the Apologiſts, contrary to the application that I made thereof. The ground that I had to apply the aſſertion to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113716:11"/>
Apologiſts is taken from their owne words in the cloſe of their Apologie; where to my beſt underſtanding they ſay plainly of their owne way, that is differs but a little from their Presbyterian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; which ſeemes to contradict the ſpeech of your obſervation, when you ſay that in the apprehenſion of the Apologiſts, the cauſe of ſeparation is great, and little in the judgement of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians. But if you marke the argument which they uſe to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it will be found this: That which differs but a little from the way which you allow, you may ſafely tolerate. But the way which we deſire to follow differs but a little from that which you allow. Therefore you may ſafely tolerate it and grant our ſuit. But if you make the argument thus: Becauſe the way which we deſire to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low is greatly different from that which you allow; therefore you ſhould grant us a Toleration; I ſuppoſe this would bee no ſtrong perſwaſion, and no part of the Apologiſts meaning.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeake of the thing in it ſelfe, as you apprehend and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it: I confeſſe that nothing which doth relate conſcience, as to conſcience, can juſtly be counted ſmall; yet the difference of things in reſpect of each other may be ſmall when you compare them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: but if a mans conſcience be troubled at that ſmall difference, it is to him no ſmall matter to digeſt it; if he makes truly conſcience of his wayes: but if his owne conſcience be not ſound, nothing will be of great moment to it, or elſe every thing of too great: for it will alwayes be in the one or other extream.</p>
            <p>Now a good and ſound conſcience is that which is enlightned by a rule to determine all that it doth: For in matters of Religion, if I leave my conſcience at large without a rule, I make mine own will and reaſon a rule, and ſerve God, not as he requireth, but as I think good: then which nothing is more deſtructive to the glory of Gods name, whereby he is acknowledged the Father of Spirits. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt tell you, that I know no Presbyterian underſtanding himſelfe, who will alleadge, that which you ſay as you alleadge it; namely thus, that the things wherein the difference is betweene them and their diſſenting Brethren are matters of indifferency in reſpect of Church-conſtitution and government: nay I know, that many make the difference wholly fundamentall and utterly deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the conſtitution of Churches in the communion of Saints. I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113716:11"/>
wiſh they would explain themſelves, ſo as to take off the jealouſies and conſtructions which are made of their Way to their prejudice. The plea of conſcience which is pretended, muſt not be ſlighted, or unconſcionably entertained, but examined and weighed; and I hope that if the caſes which trouble their conſciences were diſtinctly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and cleerly ſhewed what the point of trouble is, that rules might be found in the Word, and by the tenor of the new Covenant might be ſo applied unto the tender conſcience, that it ſhould find eaſe; but whiles matters are caried in a cloud, and a generall plea for liberty of conſcience is ſtood upon, without reſpect to ſuch duties, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with a good conſcience to be neglected amongſt brethren, there is great cauſe to fear, that there may be much deceit in ſuch a plea: For where the liberty, which with a pretence to conſcience is pleaded for, is abuſed unconſcionably, and is without reſpect, to the end wherfore it is obtained, made an occaſion to the fleſh: there may be a ſtrong preſumption of deceit in ſuch a pretence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the prudencie of the righteous, will in due time make diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of that which is unſound. For we know by experience, that the conſcience may be deceived many wayes, for want of knowledge, to diſcern the rules by which it ſhould walk; and of watchfulneſſe to apply known rules unto the wayes wherein a man doth walk. All the deceits which proceed from theſe two cauſes, are <hi>in defectu;</hi> but many of theſe that plead for a liberty of conſcience, erre <hi>in exceſſu;</hi> either by miſtaking the rule, and miſapplying of it conſequently, or by a miſapprehenſion of the matter of which the difficulty is made, which is the caſe of many that make every thing moſt odious which differs from their Way, or by a kinde of habituall ſcrupuloſitie, which makes them fearfull of every thing, ſo that they can reſt no where at firſt; and then being wearyed out of that frame of ſpirit, they take ſometimes up ſuch large principles, that they caſt off all fear, and doubting of nothing, do whatſoever they pleaſe at laſt. There be ſome that pretend conſcience unconſcionably; that is, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly, without judgement and conſideration of the reaſon why they make a ſcruple; theſe mens will, rules their conſcience, and the liberty which they affect only to pleaſe themſelves, is pleaded for, under the name of conſcience; and I am much afraid, that ſince the raiſing of theſe controverſies, about matters of conſcience amongſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113716:12"/>
brethren, which have been agitated with ſome heat, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to ſome outward priviledges in the ſtate; that the plea of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may be corpupted with humane paſſions, and worldly ends in many: For, when mens affections are raiſed with zeale for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular cauſe, relating to conſcience, if then they do not in humility reflect upon themſelves, to look to the rule of charity, that they may conſider other therein, to interpret their actions in the beſt ſenſe, to behave themſelves unblameably, in affections in word and deed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: if (I ſay) they do not this on the one ſide, but on the other ſide, looking upon theſe that are of a different Way, with an eye of jealouſie, to compare themſelves with others, and their own freedome with the freedome of other; if then their zeal for their own intereſt heat their paſſions, it is no wonder; and where hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane paſſions are once ſet awork, there the conſcience will be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and led into error, and the plea thereof will ariſe more from the will, then from the judgement. Now, in all theſe, and many more reſpects, the plea of conſcience ſhould be examined, in reſpect of all the cauſes and circumſtances thereof, that it may be rightly ſtated; not that any may take upon him to be a Judge over another mans conſcience, but that by an unpartiall diſquirie of matters, belonging to the myſtery of goldlineſſe &amp; of iniquity in the conſciences of men; rules may be propoſed according to the Word, and by the indictment of the Spirit, which will diſcover to the heart of man within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to others alſo that judiciouſly weigh matters, what truth or falſhood is in the plea and pretence of conſcience, and the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of every one within it ſelf, being helped by the Word, which is a diſcerner of the thoughts of the heart, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 12. will be laid open to it ſelf, and made a judge of its one pretences, from what grounds they ariſe, whether ſound or unſound. And to help you in this diſquirie of your ſelf, let me offer you a Principle or two of truth, which I ſuppoſe are appliable to all mens caſes and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That nothing may or, ought to trouble the conſcience, which doth not tend to a breach of the new Covenant, by which it ſtands in the favour of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That nothing can tend to a breach of the new Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and us, which is a means to increaſe his love in our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113716:12"/>
hearts towards others, and may engage us to do ſervice unto others, as Chriſt did to us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That if any have a ſcruple of conſcience, concerning any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of duty, or behaviour towards God or man, that by a right diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie of the nature of it, compared with the tenor of the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the purpoſe of Gods love towards us therein, he ſhall be able to finde a reſolution of his ſcruple.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That in caſe any upon pretence of conſcience doth refuſe that which another upon the like pretence, doth challenge as a duty of love from him, and doth offer reciprocally to perform towards him, then he that is the refuſer, is bound to ſhew from the tenor of the covenant the cauſe of his ſcruple, how in his judgement, that which is required of him, cannot ſtand with the purpoſe of Gods love to mankinde in Chriſt Jeſus and ought by all means to ſatisfie the other in what he ſhall require of him to that effect. Conſider theſe rules, and if you have any doubt concerning them, I ſhall be willing as God ſhall inable me with grace to cleere them to you.</p>
            <p>Sir, in the cloſe of this your ſecond Obſervation, you have ſome unſavory and uncharitable expreſſions, which if you will take into your ſecond conſideration, and reſlect upon them, to ſee from what Principle they proceeded in you when you wrote them, I make no doubt, but that you will diſcover ſomewhat of paſſion, of humane jealouſie, and want of Chriſtian charity in them; and ſo I leave them to be rectified in you by the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Gal.</hi> Chap. 6. 1. till verſ. 4.</p>
            <p>3. The third obſervation upon that which I ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. of the duty of gentleneſſe in Gods ſervants to abſtain from ſtrife, is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of the former complaint, and accuſation whereof I doubt you will hardly give good proof: As to the generall, I am ſure the way doth not lead to ſuch a practice; what particular faults may be in ſome, none can anſwer for: It is wiſdome and charity to deal with particulars in a particular way to recover them, and not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their faults to all.</p>
            <p>4. The fourth obſervation is upon <hi>pag.</hi> 24. concerning the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iture of ſpirituall rights and liberties, where to prevent miſtakes, I will now open my ſelf more fully then that diſcourſe did require. I ſay then thus: If men, who pretend to be brethren in Chriſt, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113716:13"/>
ſettle their mutuall relation of Brotherhood in a friendly way amongſt themſelves without ſuch debates and quarrels as tend to the ſcandall of Chriſtianity, and diſturbance of the publike peace, that then God doth allow others, (namely, his publike Vicegerents in the State) to look to their ways, and to take authority over them, ſo as to order their publike courſes for the prevention of ſuch inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But in caſe they can agree amongſt themſelves according to the Will of God, for their mutuall edification in love, then he hath no ſuch power to preſcribe any ſuch courſe unto them. If you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the caſe rightly, as I make it, I ſuppoſe you will not at all ſcruple; for my full meaning is this. That brethren in Chriſt, have a right and priviledge from Chriſt to ſettle the wayes of their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly profeſſion of Chriſtianity amongſt themſelves; that is, of edifying each other, and of preventing offenſive carriages, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one another, and towards forrainers: nor can any man on earth deprive them of this right and priviledge, ſo long as they uſe it in ſpirituall matters for the true end; but if they abuſe it to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, or make no uſe at all of it, but fall to quarrelling about it, or about other matters, and with their quarrels diſhonour their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and diſturb the peace of others, then Chriſt hath ſet one to look unto them, to prevent and rectifie the inconveniencies which ariſe from their unrulineſſe.</p>
            <p>Now, if I underſtand your ſcruple rightly, you ſay nothing to my apprehenſion againſt this caſe, becauſe I grant fully that Chriſt hath purchaſed for us our Chriſtian rights and priviledges, and given power to uſe them for edification, and not for deſtruction of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. I grant alſo, that if we uſe them ſo, then no ſtate, government, or body in this world, may abridge us of them; but I deny that no miſdemeanors can be a juſt cauſe to abridge us of ſuch rights and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges as ſerve to order our own wayes in the publike profeſſion: For, if our miſdemeanor be ſuch as may diſturb the quiet of others, then, I ſay, that the Magiſtrate, as Chriſts Vicegerent, over the publike ſociety, wherein and the outward human relations under which, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the lawes of nature, we live together, with theſe, others hath a right to order theſe courſes which are hurtfull to others, to make them harmleſſe, and free from offences. I may confeſſe, that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent opinions and Church-ways, do not neceſſarily infer a diviſion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113716:13"/>
in the ſtate; becauſe it is poſſible that men may be peaceable and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly in publike courſes, not withſtanding their private differences: but yet we ſee by experience that ordinarily in all ages and places, the difference of mens wayes in ſpirituall matters doth inferre a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion in Affections, and the diviſion of Affections, a diviſion in outward carriages and relations; and this a diviſion in ſtate matters: becauſe naturally private men aſpire to make their differences publike; and by gaining Adherents, they come at laſt to faſten an intereſt of ſtate upon themſelves, and ſo diſturbe the ſtate ſo farre as their intereſt doth reach. If you acknowledge that the diſturbers of a ſtate may be puniſhed with death; you cannot deny to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the right of inſpection over the cauſes of diſturbance; and the power to uſe prevention, leſt the effects of evill cauſes breake forth into inconveniencies.</p>
            <p>As for the priviledges of ſearching the Scriptures, of trying the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men, and examining doctrins, &amp; ſuch like: God forbid that they ſhould be abridged: but to have a priviledge of practiſing at large and in publick whatſoever any ſhal pretend to be his conſcience, and Religion, and that the Magiſtrate may not have any thing to ſay to mens publicke wayes in ſuch a kinde, is a thing which I doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: yet I would not have you thinke, that I allow of all manner of compulſion and coercive power over the Conſciences of men, which is practiſed among ſuch as endeavour to blinde the weake and vulgar ſort, that they may rule over them according to their owne will by an implicit faith: But how farre the coercive power of the Magiſtrate doth goe, in taking away the cauſes of offences, I ſuppoſe may be gathered from Pſal. 101. and now it is not fit for me to enlarge my ſelfe upon that ſubject.</p>
            <p>5. The fifth Obſervation upon <hi>pag.</hi> 25. is a doubt how the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude doth hold between a private Chriſtian and a publicke State. I anſwer: 1. It doth hold in that for which I alleadge it. 2. It doth hold proportionally each being taken in his ſphere, and according to his principles. 3. It doth not hold in all imaginable circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as one and the ſame thing, <hi>Nullum ſimile eſt idem,</hi> nothing that is like is the very ſame, and your exception is no difficulty: For as a publicke State may ſuffer, thwart, croſſe and contradictory opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be beleeved, by its ſubjects and yet ſubſiſt: So a private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113716:14"/>
may ſuffer the trouble of croſſe and contradictory thoughts, and doubtfull opinions, and yet remaine a good and conſcionable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, till God cleer his judgement.</p>
            <p>And to that which you require upon <hi>pag.</hi> 26. concerning the courſe of an orderly Conference; that I ſhould ſtate it: I ſay, that that might eaſily be done, if men could be obliged to follow it. In all Conferences men ſhew themſelves men, and have an Art of fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing: from which (till God teach them fully to deny themſelves) they cannot be brought, chiefly when they have ſet their Aime, they will have their owne way to proſecute it, and then when they can goe no further and loſe their Aime, they fall a complaining and tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtories of each other, to their prejudice and reproach. In the following part of this Obſervation you ſpeake of the Magiſtrates Power: where againe, I ſee you miſtake my meaning; therefore to informe you aright, I muſt tell you, 1. That Chriſtian Magiſtrates are not appointed by God, to ſet up an outward and viſible wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: but their duty is to authoriſe, protect and maintaine that which God in his word requireth. 2. They are <hi>Cuſtodes utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabulae,</hi> to overſee the wayes of the Churches as they relate the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and of the Miniſters thereof, to uſe meanes towards them that the duties which Chriſt requires may be performed: and in caſe of neglect to preſſe them by authority to the performance thereof. 3. I give them no ſuch inſpection over the Churches which is Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, to vindicate and puniſh faults <hi>in fore interiori;</hi> but only to hinder miſdemeanours which are publikely obſervable. 4. The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are bound if it be required of them to give them an account of all their proceedings with all due reſpect, that they may know the order of their wayes in all things, becauſe nothing ought to bee done in the darke, or concealed from his cognizance. As for that which I ſay of a States conſcience, that it ought to be like unto the conſcience of a good Chriſtian, my meaning is; that as a Chriſtian in his private ſphere muſt rule himſelfe and thoſe that are under him conſcionably to Gods glory: ſo the Councell of State is bound in its ſphere to doe the like: and though this ought to be ſo, yet your inference is not good, that therefore any man muſt reſigne his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to anothers mans will and conceptions: for all this is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected upon a miſtake. In a word, I allow of no dominion over any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113716:14"/>
mans faith or conſcience; but only as a Miniſteriall ſervice according to the Word, wherein both the Magiſtrate and the Church-officer is to learn his duty, and thereby Chriſt is to rule over the State and Church viſibly and inviſibly, in the outward and inward, bodily and ſpirituall relations.</p>
            <p>6. The ſixth obſervation upon <hi>pag.</hi> 28, 29. is anſwered already, if the caſe be rightly underſtood, and you will finde your miſtake to lie in the civill and ſpirituall ſpheres, in which the Magiſtracy and Miniſtery ought to walk: For, if they keep each within their own ſpheres, there will never be cauſe of conteſt; for the ſpirituall hath no power over the civill government, nor the civill over the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all as ſuch, but only in caſes of miſdemeanor. And in this caſe only, I ſay, that the Magiſtrate hath power to hinder a people in the chooſing of a Teacher, when they do it not orderly, but tumultuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or when a Miniſter in a factious and violent manner, or otherwiſe diſorderly thruſts himſelf upon a people, he may, and ought to take cognizance of the matter, and ſee good order &amp; peace kept according to the rules of Eccleſiaſticall government. Therefore let every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in Gods name, have his full liberty to try the ſpirits, and to hear all, and hold faſt that which is good; but let him uſe his liberty or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and give no juſt cauſe of complaint, or grievance unto others.</p>
            <p>7. In your ſeventh obſervation upon <hi>p.</hi> 36. you plead again for the freedome of diſputes, and to follow that which is beſt; which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended to reſtrain; only let it be regular, and for the end of edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, without vain jangling and confuſedneſſe of ſtrife and paſſion.</p>
            <p>8. The eight obſervation upon <hi>p.</hi> 30. concerning the power of the Magiſtrate in Church-matters, I will admit, if taken in the ſenſe which I have formerly delivered.</p>
            <p>9. To the ninth obſervation upon <hi>pag.</hi> 31. I ſay, that God doth not require that we ſhould walk after any light, but that which is the true light, which enlightneth every man that cometh into this world; therefore all are bound to ſeek that light, and never reſt till they finde it. It is true, that no man can follow any other light, but that which ſeemeth to him to be true according to his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but thence it doth not follow that wee may ſtrive and conteſt without end for every thing that to us appeares to be truth: the weight of matters is to be conſidered with diſcretion;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113716:15"/>
and becauſe no man will preſume to be infallible, the way of propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſenſe of truths, ought to be ſuch, as may declare that we can bear diffenters, and are not unwilling to admit of further light, if offered unto us from the Word. And although a Synod, or Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell hath no infallibility annexed to the Decrees thereof; yet there is ſome difference to be made between the private opinion of one, and the conſent of many, whoſe praiſes are in the Churches. This conſent of many atteſting the ſame matter as a truth, doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige men that are of an humble Spirit, and love not to be wiſe in themſelves, to conſider things more exactly, wherein their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment differs, then otherwiſe they would do. And if they cannot finde light enough to aſſent unto them, yet diſcretion will require a moderation in diſſenting; excepting ſome invincible and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratively convincing reaſons can be alledged, why it is neceſſary both to diſſent and to profeſſe a diſagreement; and yet in this caſe the profeſſed diſagreement of judgement ſhould be without breach of brotherly love, and with the preſervation of the unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in matters of undoubted practice for mutuall edification; at leaſt ſo far as in us lieth: For the Apoſtolicall rule, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 16. So <hi>far a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we are come, let us walk by one rule, and let us mind the ſame thing:</hi> is never to be refuſed on our part, if offered by others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor neglected, if it may be obtained, how far ſoever we differ in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from others in matters extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundamentall.</p>
            <p>10. To the tenth obſervation upon <hi>pag.</hi> 32. concerning a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly correſpondency in a Presbyterie, which you allow of, ſo long as it doth continue brotherly: I have this to ſay; that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident your feares of being driven by rods and ſtaves from your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heaven will be needleſſe: For the Presbyterian way doth ceaſe to be Presbyterian if it be not ſociall as between confederates, who in all things are equall one to another; ſo that all alike judge and all are alike judged, and every thing is done by common conſent and counſel; nor are any rights taken from private Churches, but rather confirmed and ſtrengthered to them: As for the ſeparation which you call in your opinion juſt, to which, for ſome reſpects you think your ſelves forced unto; I know not what elſe to ſay, but that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how it may be juſt or lawfull, for any to ſeparate from a true Church, for cauſes not laid open to them; and for matters extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundamentall.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113716:15"/>
For although I finde things in my Brethren <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, which are very offenſive to me, and might perhaps amount in my opinion, to a juſt cauſe of ſeparating from them: yet before it is lawfull for me actually to ſeparate, I am bound in all meekneſſe, firſt to beare witneſſe of thoſe things unto them, and ſeek redreſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, letting them ſee the grievance which they bring unto my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and then if they will neither redreſſe the cauſes of my grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, nor ſatisfie my judgement in an orderly way; but caſt me out from them, not at all taking notice of my complaints: if (I ſay) in dealing thus, I be thus dealt withall, then I may, and not till then be ſeparate. So that I am ſo farre from thinking it lawfull for ſome reſpects grounded upon mine owne opinion to intend a ſeparation from Brethren in the faith; that except they caſt me out, and will not ſuffer me to be of their ſociety any longer, I may not breake off from them.</p>
            <p>11. Your eleventh Obſervation upon <hi>pag.</hi> 34. concerning Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentalls in practiſe and knowledge, tends to juſtifie the deſire of the Apologiſts, to be permitted to doe or not to doe what they thinke requiſite; but you mention nothing in particular, which may be counted Fundamentall in their profeſſion; for which only a ſeparation is juſtifiable when duly atteſted; and not only not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but rejected together with the witneſſe bearers. Now the caſe between them and their Brethren is quite contrary at this preſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for they have been and are deſired to hold forth the Truth of their way, but they doe decline it, and yet will be ſeparate although they acknowledge the Churches to be true Churches from which they depart: and although thoſe Brethren from whom they depart, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to offer them all equitable forbearance and redreſſe of their grievances, ſo farre as can ſtand with the Fundamentall conſtitution of their owne Churches and the peace of their conſciences.</p>
            <p>12. Your twelfth and laſt Obſervation upon <hi>pag.</hi> 37. wherein you ſpeake, of the ſubjection which members owe to their Paſtor, and conſequently to the Presbytery of Paſtors joyned with him, is ſomewhat dark to me. For firſt, you ſeem to yeeld the Point; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſuch a ſubjection is due, and then you make a reſtriction thereof in reſpect of certaine things, and in reſpect of the manner of cenſuring them in caſe of not ſubmitting. You ſay then (if I take
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113716:16"/>
you right) that they are bound to ſubmit to a Presbytery, in things only, unto which they may yeeld with a good conſcience. This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed, but is needleſſe to be alleadged, becauſe it is to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that a Paſtor joyned with a Presbytery will require no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection but in things which may be yeelded unto with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. For their proper worke is to deale with the conſciences of thoſe that are under their charge, to informe them of Gods will, that they may underſtandingly ſubmit unto it. That which is offered by them to others is not offered. Authoritatively as a thing which they will have done; becauſe they ſo have determined it (this is the language of worldly States unto their ſubjects:) but they offer it as ſervants of God, to declare, as his meſſengers, by the word, his will; for they watch in all caſes of common concernment over the ſoules of men; and in this reſpect obedience and ſubmiſſion is commanded by the Apoſtle to be yeelded unto them, Heb. 13. 17. But you will put the caſe that he who is directed in matters of conſcience by a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, findeth reaſon to diſſent, becauſe he is not convicted in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that the direction is according to the word of God: in this Caſe you ſay that the Presbytery hath no power to deale with him, but that he is lyable to be cenſured only by his own Church, under whoſe juriſdiction he ſtandeth. Here I ſuppoſe you ſpeake of the point of juriſdiction in a humane ſenſe, and ſuppoſe in all this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that which is deſtructive to the true communion of Saints and to the relation which Chriſt hath ſetled in the parts of his Church fitly compacted together and baptized into one body by his Spirit. For you ſuppoſe your Paſtor and his Congregation under whoſe cenſure alone you would ſtand, to be alone a Body by it ſelfe and ſeparate from the other Paſtors and Congregations: I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it to be a Body by it ſelfe: but if you ſuppoſe a Presbytery rightly conſtituted with it, then it is not to be conſidered as ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, but as compacted and a part of the reſt of that which is the whole; and as you ſtand in relation to that Congregation whereof you are an immediate member; ſo it doth ſtand proportionally in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to that Body to which it is combined as a part. As then you are under the juriſdiction of your owne Paſtor and Congregation by your own confeſſion immediately; ſo you muſt be mediatly by their means under the juriſdiction of that Body whereof they are a part,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113716:16"/>
and whereunto they are aſſociated. But if you will not grant any ſuch aſſociating &amp; compacting of Churches together into one Body, for their mutuall edification (which is certainly Chriſts clear intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Eph. 4. 1. till 17.) but will ſuppoſe that all Churches and their Paſtors muſt ſtand ſingle and ſeparate by themſelves; then it is to be granted that you are under the juriſdiction of none but your owne Paſtor and Elderſhip. But ſuppoſing that which cannot bee denyed (if you grant it lawfull to combine Paſtors and Elderſhips into a Presbytery, which I ſuppoſe I have fully proved) that your Paſtor and his Elderſhip is accountable in his proceedings to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Brethren, as they are accountable unto him for mutuall edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: and that he finding you a refractory and unruly member of his flocke, diſturbing the peace thereof; and having dealt with you as much as he could, and yet hath not been able to bring you to the obedience and ſubmiſſion which you owe to the will of God, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing this to be ſo, if then he to ſtrengthen himſelfe and his Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by counſell firſt doth bring the matter to the Presbytery; and having received counſell and put it in execution, doth finde it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effect: you remaining ſtill diſobedient, and diſturbing the quiet of his owne, and perhaps of ſome neighbour Churches; may not he then in the ſecond place deſire the aſſiſtance of his confederates in the judgement of the matter? and may not he call you before them to be cenſured by himſelfe and them joyntly? and his and their juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction being in this caſe but one in Chriſt: and the authority of the ſame Presbyteriall office being put forth by all at once through the ſame ſpirit in the name of Chriſt; doe not you thinke that the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of judgement againſt you will bee ratified in heaven if it be rightly pronounced? or doe you thinke that Chriſt will allow of this plea, that you are exempted from their juriſdiction, becauſe they are not your immediate Paſtors? hath not Chriſt given to the combined ſociety of Church officers a power to judge of matters according to the word, when they are in an orderly way brought unto their arbitration? and where there is a power to judge by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an office, there alſo a power to pronounce a ſentence cannot be denyed: and if the ſentence be a cenſure, the ſame Authority which doth pronounce it, hath power to ſee it executed. Suppoſe againe on the other ſide that a Paſtor doth ſome injury to his flocke,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113716:17"/>
or to ſome one of them; and that they or he cannot finde redreſſe at the hands of the Elderſhip; if there be no Aſſociation of Elderſhips, they or he have no remedy but to make a trouble, and perhaps a rent in the Congregation; but if there be a Presbytery under which this Paſtor doth ſtand as a member; the matter may be brought unto them, and he who is the Paſtor in that caſe will be cenſurable, if hee be in a fault; all that in theſe caſes can be pretended is, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is firſt to be judged and conſidered by the immediate Elderſhip, and then by the Presbytery; and when the cenſure is to be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, it is to be given out, by his owne Paſtor, in his owne name and in the name of all: Theſe matters of outward order, if they can take away the ſcruples of ſuch as ſtand upon pointilloes of Right and Juriſdiction after the manner of men; and if they can prevent and heale our dangerous breaches and diviſions, ſhould by all meanes be yeelded unto. But if men wil be content with nothing but with ſuch a Church-conſtitution wherein they can upon the matter doe what they will; and make lawes and breake them as they thinke good, and rule by the ſenſe of the multitude, (whom they can poſſeſſe with jealouſies and ſway for ends and intereſts) their officers, by whom they ought to be ruled; and to this purpoſe ſtand ſeparate, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all Aſſociation of Church Elderſhips, leſt they ſhould bee ſtrengthned by their mutuall conſent, counſell, and joynt Authority: if I ſay, men will be content with nothing but this, and if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get this undue liberty, will poſſeſſe themſelves and others with jealouſies, and trouble thereby their owne and other weake conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences with feares and ſcruples, it is a ſad condition and a dolefull preſage that the Candleſticke will be removed from this Nation; if God in mercy doth not direct the outward Authority to ſtrengthen effectually the hands of theſe that ſeeke a ſettlement of themſelves according to the rule; but if they alſo refuſe to countenance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them in the ſettlement of their union, except they will come wholly under their ſecular power to depend upon them, as upon their head in ſpiritual Judicatures, which only tend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the reforming and purging of their Congregations from ſcandales diſhonourable to the profeſſion of the Goſpell: If I ſay, the former ſort of men may hinder the ſettlement, and theſe latter will not grant a furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to it but upon this condition; we are in a ſad caſe, and for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113716:17"/>
ought that I can ſee, remedileſſe without ſome ſpeciall work of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly providence; whereunto I ſhall heartily recommend you with all that walk in your way of truth and ſimplicity, as being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate ſervant in Chriſt Jeſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
J. Dury.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>H.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Loving Friend:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou tell me that Mr. Robinſon did expect that I ſhould have anſwered ſomewhat to his demands, concerning the demonſtrative Analyſis of Holy Scripture, which with much earneſtneſſe in his Letter to me he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I ſhould put forth, at leaſt ſo farre as the matter is ripened in my thoughts; and that he doth not a little wonder, that in my whole Letter to him, wherein otherthings are ſo diſtinctly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and largely handled; this main thing whereunto chiefly he would have ingag'd me, is not ſo much as mentioned with one word. To give you ſatisfaction concerning this, that he by you may know the reaſons hereof; I would have you to take notice unto him, that what I upon occaſion have written, or ſpoken of a demonſtrative way, of analyſing the Scripture, hath rather been a declaration of my opinion, that ſuch a thing may be found out and held forth unto the world, and by Gods bleſſing, of great uſe to compoſe our diſorderly notions in Scripturall matters, then any brag of mine, that I ſhould have found out ſuch a way; for although I have endeavoured to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my ſelf in this thing, and thank God that my minde is at reſt in it, for my ordinary courſe of meditation; yet I preſume not to boaſt of any thing, extraordinary beyond others, or to make the meaſure of my rule, a Rule to others; (for this were to meaſure my ſelf by my ſelf) but I deſire ſimply to hold forth the truth, whereof I am convinced; to give others occaſion to think of it with me for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113716:18"/>
our mutuall ſettlement in peace and truth; that when it may be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and expedient, and God ſhall call me forth to propoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this nature I may be heard, and judged by ſuch as are able, without partiality to diſcern the nature of the thing which may be propoſed in this kinde: You know that I love not ſuch commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as he doth give to me in reſpect of this matter; and if I ſhould appear to entertain his motion in flattering my ſelf with them, would it not be vanity? And might not God juſtly blaſt the ſmall beginnings of light which I have received in this kinde; if I ſhould be lifted up to conceit any thing of my ſelf in regard of it? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thought it fit not to ſpeak ſo much as one word of that matter to him, upon ſuch high expreſſions as he doth uſe, leſt I might ſeem to accept of undeſerved praiſes, and attribute ſomething to my ſelf which is beyond my line. My ſilence then is no effect of any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe in me, to impart any thing to others, of that which God hath beſtowed upon me for the increaſe of knowledge, but it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated by reaſon of the want, both of time, to elaborate what is further requiſit for the manifeſtation of my ſenſe in this matter? and of opportunity to propoſe ſeaſonably that which is in ſome meaſure already elaborated, that it may be taken into conſideration, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by ſuch as are able to judge thereof. You know, that when I have bin diſcreetly &amp; ſeriouſly called upon in a private way, by men known to your ſelf, to impart my thoughts unto them of this matter, that I have never refuſed to lay open the principles of my Generall or Particular wayes of meditating in this or any other kinde; and that the maxime by which I walk is quite contrary to reſervedneſſe, therfore I hope you do not take any offence at my ſilence at this time, ſeeing you know how I am otherwiſe ſtrained, and what freedome of ſpirit is requiſite to intend ſuch weighty thoughts, and propoſe matters of ſo univerſall concernment to the view of the world: And if theſe conſiderations which neceſſitate me to lay theſe thoughts aſide till a ſit ſeaſon, do not give ſatisfaction for the grand ſilence wherein this matter is involved in my anſwer to Mr. Robinſon; you may, if you pleaſe, adde as a ſupplement to his Letter, ſome of the Tracts which in former times I have written to ſome others about<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this ſubject, whereof I ſcarce have any copies (for you know how they drop from me) but you have kept the tranſcript, I ſuppoſe, of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113716:18"/>
all, therefore, if any thing written to Sir Cheny, or to any other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be ſeaſonable to ſupply this ſeeming neglect of his deman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I ſhall not be againſt the uſe which you may m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5+ letters">
                  <desc>•••••…</desc>
               </gap> of it for this end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I am loth to leave either in you or him any ſcruple concerning any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, which ſhall always be harmleſſe unto all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and faithfull to do you ſervice in Jeſus Chriſt, in w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>His and your affectionate ſervant,
John Dury.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To Sir <hi>Cheny Culpeper</hi> Knight.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am very deſirous to gratifie you in the vertuous deſire which you have expreſſed unto me, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the method of Meditation: For, I think my ſelf a debter more to you therein, then unto others, becauſe your zeal doth lead you to more univerſall conception, then others are capable of: if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Gods will to open a door of utterance unto me, towards you at this time, at leaſt ſo far, as to initiate you fully in the way of future conference with the about this matter, I would be exceeding glad; not only for your ſake, but even for mine own ſake, that I might have a fit object to work upon, and to bring forth the particulars which lie in my minde, and which without ſome good and ſit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, I cannot be drawn to elaborate and put to paper.</p>
            <p>I am willing then at this time, to ſhew you my conceptions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the firſt principles of the Method which I think everyone ſhould follow that will walk by a rule in ordering his thoughts for Meditation and Conſultation: Here you have the aim of my preſent diſcourſe with you, wherein you may obſerve diſtinctly, that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe: Firſt, that a man is able to order his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoughts: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that the means to order them is a certain rule, by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould walk: Thirdly, that this rule hath certain principle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which now I am chiefly to ſpeak: Fourthly, and that the ends, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113716:19"/>
objects towards which the thoughts are to be ordered, are the acts of meditating and conſulting. If any body make theſe preſuppoſalls diſputable; or, if you ſhould make a doubt of them, I cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed cleerly with you, except I know where his or your ſcruple doth lie, that ſome principle wherein we can agree, may be taken up to ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it. But ſuppoſing that things are not ſo much ſcrupled and made diſputable, as not well and fully underſtood, then before I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, I muſt open the ſame unto you. I ſay then, concerning the firſt, that my meaning is not, that a man hath any ſuch command over himſelf, that all the riſings of thoughts in his minde ſhould be under his power, either to prevent thoughts which he would not have to come in his minde, or to lay down thoughts riſen, or to reduce at all times into good order the thoughts that cannot be laid down; This is not my meaning: For, I know that the preparations of the heart in man and the anſwer of the tongue is from the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 1. and that mans goings are of the Lord, and that therefore he cannot underſtand his own way in reſpect of the firſt motions thereof <hi>ibid.</hi> Chap. 20. 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to which that place of <hi>Jerem.</hi> 10. 23. is parallel: O Lord, I know that the way of man is not in himſelf, and it is not in man that walketh, to direct his ſteps, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt motions are not from a man, nor can a man by any humane inſtruction, or habituall practiſe and premeditation attain to any ſuch perfection, that he ſhall be able to direct and over-rule all his thoughts, and the actions which proceed from thence unto his own preconceived aims and ends: For, although a mans heart doth deceive his way, and laieth plots unto it ſelf, and maketh many reſolutions, yet the Lord is he who directeth a mans ſteps, towards the event thereof; ſo that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. 9.</note> the firſt motions of the mind, nor the conſtant &amp; abſolute pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe thereof is in our power; but this I mean, when I ſay that we are able to order our thoughts, <hi>viz.</hi> that the underſtanding of a man hath received from God a reflexive faculty to conſider of it ſelf and its own actions, and of all things belonging unto the motions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; to the end that they may be brought into ſome regular frame, and freed from confuſion and unſettledneſſe for the proſecution of matters whereupon the Spirit is fully bent, and ought to be fixed. This reflexive faculty is given to the nature of all mens underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but it is not in the power of every one to make uſe of it, or to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> uſe of it; For, neither can every one reflect upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113716:19"/>
and his owne motions when it is moſt expedient; not when he doth reflect upon himſelfe, and upon the acts of his underſtanding can he doe it at all times as he ought to doe it: but this ability to make uſe and to make right uſe of the reflexive faculty is a peculiar gift of God, and he doth beſtow it upon whomſoever he pleaſeth. For as Elihu ſaith to Job, There is a ſpirit in man and the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth them underſtanding: ſo it is certaine that although the faculty of ordering our wayes be in the ſoule, yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept God breath upon it and make it alive, it cannot either act or act any thing aright, but it lyeth there as a dead thing without motion whileſt a man doth walke at randome in a vaine ſhew not knowing himſelfe what he is doing; or if perhaps hee doth take notice of himſelfe what he is doing; or if perhaps hee doth take notice of himſelfe (as naturally men uſe to doe) it is rather to flatter himſelf in idle conceits and imaginations or to follow eagerly ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular plots, then to order and regulate his wayes unto true felicity, and ſubordinate his motions unto the lawfull ends for which they ſhould be undertaken.</p>
            <p>Thus I muſt be underſtood in the firſt preſuppoſall aright leſt I ſhould ſeem to attribute too much unto our owne abilities in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and exempt the motions of our heart from Gods immediate working upon it as if he did leave it wholly to a mans ſelfe; or as if by any art, method, inſtruction and direction which wee can give, any man ſhould be made able to rule all his thoughts, ſo that they ſhould be compoſed at all times to attaine to any object which hee ſhould propoſe unto himſelfe. This muſt not be thought, but my meaning is to be conceived of the ordinary faoulty of reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves how to make uſe of it in the fear of God when we find our ſelves moved to intend good and lawfull matters for our owne and others edificution: how then we ſhould frame and compoſe our Meditations and Conſultation to attaine by rule unto the end for which they are undertaken, and not to proceed as fooles and children doe at a randome, in the acts wherein reaſon and wiſdome ſhould take place, is the true object of this Diſcourſe, and the ſenſe of the firſt ſuppoſall.</p>
            <p>The ſecond preſuppoſall thinke hath no difficulty: For if a man doth grant that there is a reflexive faculty in the underſtanding, and that this faculty can act upon the thoughts, and that thoſe thoughts can be ordered and freed from confuſion, I doe not ſee how hee can
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113716:20"/>
make a doubt of this, <hi>viz.</hi> That the meanes to order our thoughts ſhould be ſome rule or other, according to which the underſtanding ſhould proceed in working upon it ſelfe. And then concerning the third in like manner, if it be granted that where order is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, there a rule may be uſed, it cannot be denyed but that in orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring things by rules, principles muſt be obſerved whence the Rules are to bee taken: For ſeeing by ordering is implyed a ſetting of things in a precedencie and conſecution one to another; and by a Rule is meant either the forme and frame, or the reaſon why the precedencie and conſecution ought to be ſo, and not otherwiſe. And ſeeing all formes and frames which are rationally compoſed have a ground in the being and nature of the thing, whence they ariſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore it cannot be denyed but that the Rules by which humane thoughts are to be ordered, muſt have certain principles; which principles we will now ſpeake of (God willing) in briefe, that you may have an overture made unto you, either to proceed by your ſelf upon the grounds that ſhall be afforded unto you, or to call upon me hereafter, and give me cauſe to open my ſelfe further in due time for your better ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>You have now already underſtood that by principles, I mean the grounds of rules by which a man is to walke in his thoughts of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and conſultation; the end then to which we drive is to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate and conſult aright: by meditating I conceive the act of the minde reflecting upon the nature of any thing to dive into the true properties and uſes thereof. By conſulting, I underſtand the act of the minde reflecting upon the actions which are to bee undertaken or left off, or not undertaken about any thing; to gaine ſome good end whereunto they ſhould be directed according as it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be or not to be poſſible or uſefull. From whence you may gather that the acts of the minde which are to be regulated (which we call meditation and conſultation) are not now to be conſidered in reſpect of the ſubjects whereupon they are to reflect (which wee have called the natures of things and the actions which may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by us for ſome good end) but in reſpect of the reflection it ſelfe, that whether we meditate or conſult, we may have a rule to order the reflection of our minde upon any ſubject whatſoever. The rule then which we ſeeke at this time is to be gathered from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the acts of the minde to ſet them in their right frame one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, and not from the relation which they may have to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113716:20"/>
w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rds the diſcovery of any thing in reſpect of outward objects: you ſee then that the acts of the minde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they have a twofold Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo they admit of a twofold Rule; for as they relate other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects beſides themſelves, they muſt be made proportionate unto the ends which the underſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in theſe objects but as they relate one another they muſt be ruled and ordered according to their owne inward properties, and made anſwerable unto the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ought to reflect one upon another. Where I obſerve, that to finde the principles whereby theſe acts are to be regulated is to diſcover three things: 1. What the acts of the mind of man are, and how they are diſtinguiſhed? 2. How they ſtand in relation one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in their ſeverall inward properties? 3. What the end of this relation is? and how it muſt be gained? for this relation is the ground of this reflection; and the end of this relation is the firſt inward prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of goodneſſe, and of that well being whereupon the nature of the ſoul of man hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and conſtituted; and from which all the well ordered acts thereof muſt naturally flow: and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not anſwerable thereunto in the agitation of thoughts &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mind is to be judged irrationall &amp; void of underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Now then to lay open the Acts of a mans minde, it is not poſſible except we know what a man and what his minde is. By a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5+ letters">
                  <desc>•••••…</desc>
               </gap> conceive this creature which we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſelves to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from all other living and ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll things by the frame of our body and of our ſoule, which the Scripture ſaith, was made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the image of God, which image of God (ſince we have loſt it) is now unknowne unto nature; and there fore by the uſe of naturall reaſon no man can know himſelfe truly what he is, becauſe he hath loſt the Idea of the image after which he was made. But the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture having told us that our body was made of the ſubſtance of the earth, and that by the breath of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d into our noſtrills we are become a livi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at God made us thus after his owne image that we ſhould under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as his ſubſtitutes bearing his image and likeneſſe in this world, have Dominion over all the reſt of the creatures which are therein. I ſay the Scripture having taught us this much; wee have by this doctrines new principle of knowledge whereby to diſcer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are, and what our minde is, and what the end is wherefore it was put in our earthly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, of which things I will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap> at large <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but in a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d I will
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113716:21"/>
tell you what according to this Scripturall truth, I conceive man and his minde to be; <hi>viz.</hi> a ſpirit, a ſoule, and a body joyned together in the powers of an eternall rationall and ſenſuall life whereof the acts ſhould be anſwerable one to another according to their predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant or ſubordinate properties, wherein they are all to be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable unto the life of God. The acts then of the life of man are threefold; ſome are ſenſuall ſome are rationall, and ſome are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. The ſenſuall ariſe from the body and its outward or inward ſenſes: the rationall ariſe from the faculties of the naturall ſoule in the imagination of the minde, in the memory, in the diſcerning and judging faculties, and in the will. The ſpirituall ariſe from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bearing witneſſe of the will of God, and of our agreement or diſagreement with the ſame. By which you ſee what is called the minde of man, whoſe acts we ſhould regulate, <hi>viz.</hi> The living faculty of the ſpirit dwelling in the conſcience, and of the rationall ſoule dwelling in the will and underſtanding. As concerning the ſenſuall life wherein we differ not from beaſts, we make it no part of the minde of man, although wee hold not that man hath more ſoules then one, or that theſe Acts of the ſenſuall life are to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and no way brought under a Rule: but we affirme both, that the ſoule is but one, and alſo that theſe Acts may and muſt be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated although we conceive that they belong not properly unto the life of the minde. Thus then we ſee what the Acts of the minde of man are, and how they are diſtinguiſhed; namely, into the Acts of the ſpirit dwelling in the conſcience, and into the acts of the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſoule dwelling in the memorative underſtanding and willing faculties, to which the whole ſenſuall life and all the acts of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward ſenſes are ſubordinate. The relation wherein theſe acts ſtand one to another in reſpect of the properties of theſe faculties whence they proceed is this, that the faculty of the ſpirit in the acts and enditements of the conſcience is ſupreme and predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant above all the reſt: to which the rationall faculty of the ſoule in the acts of memory, underſtanding and willing is immediately ſubordinate; and to theſe the acts of the imaginations and ſenſuall paſſions are ſubſervient and ſubmitted. And if this relation and ſubordination be altered, ſo that the ſenſuall ſhould be predominant above the rationall, or the rationall above the ſpirituall acts, then all is out of order, and a mans life is either beaſtly or divelliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:113716:21"/>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd wherefore this relation and ſubordination of the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of man was thus appointed and ordered by God, is, that in the right uſe of theſe faculties he ſhould expreſſe the Image and life of God, wherein he ſhould be able to rule over the reſt of the creatures, to bring them to the ſtate of happineſſe, that Gods glory might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as in himſelf: ſo alſo in every one of them according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of their perfection. So that to gain this end for which God hath thus framed the minde of man, the rule is none other, but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the true relation wherein God hath ſet us, which is, that our ſpirits ſhould be in our conſcience wholly ſubjected unto his Spirit, and dependant from him, (who is the Father of ſpirits) in all things. So that without his leave and the knowledge of his will, by reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his Word ingrafted in our hearts, we ſhould not preſume to think, ſay, or do any thing: Secondly, that our reaſon ſhould in all things be a ſervant unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndictment of the ſpirituall Word made manifeſt unto our conſcience to obey it, and to make the truth and goodneſſe thereof plain and evident to our ſelves and others: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our ſenſuall motion ſhould bee ſervant unto the preſcripts of reaſon to help our rationall faculties to expreſſe the will of God, and apply it unto thoſe with whom we have to deal outwardly.</p>
            <p>From all which you may gather, (for theſe are the principles which I did intend to ſpeak of) much more then I am able at this time to utter: For here you have a fountain of rules, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m whence many directions may be taken, how to order the acts of the minde in reſpect of their mutuall relation one to another: For, conſider that in all things whereof we do think, except they be mearly ſpirituall and divine; ſo that they are no wayes ſubject unto ſenſe, there ought to concur the act of conſcience of reaſon, and of the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, which is the inward ſenſe, and the head of all the other ſenſuall faculties; and ſeeing theſe acts ſhould continually concurre in all the minding of outward matters, the rule is, that they muſt not be confounded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor prepoſterouſly brought forth; but that we ſhould firſt order the acts of our minde within it ſelf before we proceed to meditate upon any particular object<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For, except the conſcience be cleer and at reſt in reſpect of God, the underſtanding will not perform the duty aright and if the underſtanding faculty be out of order, the ſenſes will not be well imployed adminiſter and ſeek out evidences, or to repreſent them orderly unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113716:22"/>
abilities: So that to lay the firſt ground work of meditation and conſultation aright, a man of judgement ſhould look to himſelf, that theſe three great wheels of the mind, be well compoſed and ſer in order one towards another; the conſcience, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the ſenſitive faculty, leſt the conſcience being under guilt and deſilements, be ſeparate from God, who is the author of all good gifts, and from whoſe mouth alone wiſdome doth proceed,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. 6. for God doth not give true wiſdome and underſtanding, but unto ſuch as come to him to ſeek it: Now, to come to him or to ſeek wiſdome from him without faith, it is neither poſſible nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any thing be received at his hand; for without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. And he that is of a doubting and waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mind, muſt not think that he can receive any thing of the Lord, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 6, 7. But when the conſcience is not cleanſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from dead works, there muſt needs be a doubting, and wavering in it, when it cometh before God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo it will be found unfit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive wiſdome or direction from him.</p>
            <p>For God giveth to a man that is good in his ſight, wiſdome and knowledge, and joy, but to the ſinner he giveth travell, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 26. nor can wiſdome enter or find place into an unclean ſoul, becauſe it is prepoſſeſſed with ſin, which maketh a ſeparation betwixt God<note place="margin">Iſai. 59. 8.</note> and it. Beſides all which, it is to be conſidered, that as the fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdome, ſo the ſpirit that hath not a dependency upon the Word of the Lord, can have no wiſdome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Jeremiah ſaith: That ſeeing they have rejected the Word of<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erem. 8. 9.</note> the Lord, what wiſdome is in them? There can be no wiſdome where the Word of the Lord is not regarded; and this Word cannot be regarded, except the heart he poſſeſſed with his fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this cannot be except the conſcience be ſanctified and cleanſed from dead works: So that we ſee the firſt principl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and preparative unto me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, muſt be the compoſing of the heart towards God, to ſet our ſelves to think of that which is to be thought God, to ſet our ſelves to think of that which is to be thought upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in his preſence, through his fear depending upon his Word, and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing his direction; that not only with his leave and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6+ letters">
                  <desc>••••••…</desc>
               </gap>ion but by his order, and according to his will, we may do all things and think all our thoughts. This prediſpoſing of the mind towards God, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect firſt upon him in all our meditations, is like unto the tuning of an Inſtrument, before a man doth begin to play a piece of good Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113716:22"/>
ſo, by drawing neer to God with a good conſcience, in clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it from all ſuperfluity of naughtinſſe, and calling upon him by faith for grace and direction, the ſtrings of the ſoul are tuned and ſet in a good harmony, that the Spirit of wiſdome which proceedeth from him may play ſome harmonious melodicall piece upon the ſame, which without this tuning of the ſoul, cannot be done: And this tuning cannot be performed, except the conſcience be brought neer unto God, and be able to look upon him, that it may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned: For, by looking to him, and comparing it ſelf to his will and living Word, it receiveth light; Firſt, to ſee and judge it ſelf in what eſtate it is, and then to judge other things alſo; for then it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecteth upon all things, (and chiefly upon the inferiour faculties, which are ſubordinate unto the motions of the Spirit) with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding power; ſo that they all ſtoop and yeeld to it, to become anſwerable unto the intentions of the Spirit, which are conceived by a good conſcience to be aimed at in the work of meditation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation: And let every man, who deſireth to go ſafe in any buſineſſe of conſequence, be ſure that he never fall to work without this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative; for without it, he may run himſelf into errors, and thoſe very dangerous, and he cannot poſſibly walk by true light and rules, as long as the great Maſter rule, and principle of light is not made uſe of, which is the ſubordination of the intents and purpoſes of the heart unto God, to ſet it in frame, which may be anſwerable unto his will. This then is the firſt main Principle of true order, to be ſettled in the thoughts to bring the conſcience to reflect upon God, and ſettle it ſelf towards him in the buſineſſe which is to be minded.</p>
            <p>The ſecond main principle is, to have a care to cleer the naturall underſtanding, from prejudices and foreſtalled opinions, which are like filmes over the eyes of the minde, through which it cannot look ſo, as to diſcern the right ſhape of things, otherwiſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſufficiently apparent.</p>
            <p>Theſe prejudices ariſe from a narrowneſſe and ſtinting of the thoughts unto things too particular; therefore, before we begin to meditate or conſult, we ſhould abſtract from particulars, and ſtate the queſtion whereof we are to think in generall termes, which ſhould comprehend the true nature of particulars, which being done, the terms of the queſtion are to be conſidered and examined, that the properties thereof may be diſcovered. To which effect the acts
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113716:23"/>
of ratiocination ſhould be obſerved and rightly ordered, which are:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To diſcern diſtinctly the differences of matters belonging to the terms of the queſtion.</item>
               <item>2. To compare thoſe diſtinct matters together with the thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after; that from their agreement or diſagreement, the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may gather the reſolution of the queſtion.</item>
               <item>3. To apply the queſtion generally reſolved, unto the Particular matter in hand; where the circumſtances of the particular are to be lookt into, to ſinde how far they anſwer, or anſwer not unto the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall determination of the queſtion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thus then the acts of Ratiocination ſhould proceed by degrees: For, the main Principle, whereby they are to be regulated, is this, that the underſtanding muſt proceed always from things foreknown to that which is unknown, by ſingle notions, to proceed unto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponuds, which may be done, either from generalls, foreknowne, to determine particulars unknown: or, from particulars foreknown, to gather the generall notion wherein they all agree; for both wayes the reaſoning faculty ſhould proceed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſtate the queſtion which is to be made the ſubject of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, by ſumming up the particulars foreknown, into one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall head and property of their agreement.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to reſolve that queſtion into its diſtinct matters, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the properties thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to compare thoſe properties with the thing ſought after to ſee what they will diſcover of it in generall. And,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, to apply that which ſhall be diſcovered in generall, to the particular, as it ſtandeth under its circumſtances. And to this laſt act of reaſoning, which concerneth the circunſtances of particular matters, the uſe of ſenſe doth concurre to enquire, obſerve, diſcern, and help to compare things together, by their out wardly perceptible qualities, which lead the underſtanding to the apprehenſion of more inward properties.</p>
            <p>Now, the Principle by which the acts of ſenſe are to be regulated, is this, that they ſhould be kept from confuſed wanderings, and be made to reſlect upon the obſervation of circumſtances, according to the ſuggeſtion of reaſon in the order by which matters are to be compared one with another; for except circumſtances be taken in their right places, the application will not be cleer, nor rightly made.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113716:23"/>
The imagination then, and the memory (which have received the Ideas of circumſtances obſerved by outward ſenſe) muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; to make report of the ſame in that order, and for ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, which reaſon ſubordinate unto conſcience ſhall require to bee done; for the deciſion of that which is enquired after by way of Meditation and Conſultation. And if theſe principles of order in the acts of the minde within it ſelfe be carefully obſerved, I ſuppoſe no man can doubt but that the progreſſe will be effectuall towards the diſcovery of Truth in the objects of Meditation, and of goodneſſe in the objects of Conſultation. For all the worke the minde of man is ſet upon, is nothing elſe but Truth and Goodneſſe, to finde the ſame in Matters and Actions. And becauſe Truth and Goodneſſe are complicated together, ſo that the one is never without the other, therefore they are ſought joyntly, and never found but together. But the inſtinct of nature leadeth men more to deſire goodneſſe then truth; is ſought becauſe it is knowne to be good but the notion of goodneſſe is different in the capacities of men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſought differently according to the apprehenſions which men have of it: For ſome apprehend nothing to be good, but what is anſwerable unto the delight which they take in ſenſuall objects: others apprehend the goodneſſe of rationall objects; and ſome are exalted unto ſpirituall objects. Whence we finde three ſorts of men in the world: ſome (but few are ſuch) ſeek before all things and in all things, the goodneſſe which proceedeth immediatly from God in the life of the Spirit. Others, who live in a rationall and morall way, content themſelves with the fruits of naturall knowledge, in the workes of their underſtanding.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, ſome live in their ſenſuall appetites as beaſts doe. The firſt ſort of men are Citizens of heaven. The ſecond are Rulers of this world; the third are ſlaves of the world. Theſe different pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of men, are to be found more or leſſe in all the Meditations and Conſultations of men about particular objects. For when the minds of men runne chiefly upon temporall matters to ſeek bodily caſe and contentment unto themſelves in all things whereof they meditate and conſult; they debaſe the uſe of their reaſon, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it to become a ſlave unto luſt. And if they reſt in a temporall content of things not meerly bodily, but ſomewhat alſo rationall: To have power and honour, and preheminence, to rule over others
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113716:24"/>
by their underſtanding, they are in ſome degree better then others, but yet not truly ſet upon that which is good. And therefore none but ſuch as in the Acts of Meditation and Conſultation, raiſe their thoughts, firſt to ſpirituall good, which is permanent unto life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: And then comprehend under it as ſubordinate matters there unto, the objects of reaſon and ſenſe. Now (Iſay) but ſuch order their thoughts aright, and whoſoever walketh by this Rule, hee may expect, that in ſeeking the Kingdome of God, other things ſhall be added unto him, according to the promiſe of Chriſt, Mat. 6. 33. Now becauſe I labour in the wayes of my calling, and in all the Meditations which I uſe to propoſe unto others, to draw mens thoughts unto this rule, therefore although none doth contradict the propoſalls which I make; yet I finde that they are not much reliſhed; becauſe moſt men, even of this Calling wherein I live, ſeek not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which is ſpirituall, but rather that which is temporall, either in a rationall or ſenſuall way: for except they can perceive a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular preſent advantage of honour and credit, or of profit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they never care for that which is ſpirituall: And this is the cauſe why I cannot ſinde a Patron for my worke, becauſe I doe not ſet my minde, to ſerve ends and particular intereſts, unto which all parties now adayes are wedded; and can reliſh nothing but what is lubordinate thereunto.</p>
            <p>This then is the combate which I have to fight with the ſpirits of men; namely, to bring them from their private Aimes, to a true ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall good, wherein the glory of God, and the ſalvation of ſoules, without any other reſpects may be advanced.</p>
            <p>I have added this Digreſſion to let you ſee, that I neither can nor will expect promotion for my endeavours, but from ſuch as can and will follow with me theſe principles of Meditation, and Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to joyne with me therein to further the publike good, whereat I aime. For except mens aime concur, there can be no reall conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of endeavours And it is not lawfull for me to leave my aime and way of meditation to ſerve inferiour ends; and ſeeing they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not raiſe their thoughts, to walke with me by theſe rules, I am like to be as I am, continually deſerted, yet I am not diſcouraged; for I know that my reward is with him, whom I ſerve, and he in due time is able to open mens eyes, to ſee that they weary themſelves for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and wander in the fooliſhneſſe of troubleſome councels, ſo long
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113716:24"/>
as they follow not theſe grounds of meditation. For all the plots and purpoſes of men, meerly rationall, though never ſo plauſibly and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid, will vaniſh when the Kingdome of God draweth neer, which is now at hand, and then nothing but what is truly univerſall and ſpirituall ſhall remain. If then we do not intend to loſe our labour, and be fruſtrate of our reward, we ſhould ſow to the Spirit, by a ſound way of ſpirituall meditation and conſultation in all matters which we take in hand: That every purpoſe wherein we deſire to walk rationally amongſt men, and to apply our ſenſes in a right courſe, may be firſt conſidered, as in the preſence of God conſcionably.</p>
            <p>Theſe generall Principles of meditation, by the grace of God, may be uſefull for the ordering of our thoughts in particular objects, if accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of theſe grounds, rules be delivered to direct the acts of the mind in the diſquirie of doubtfull matters as well rationall and humane, as ſpirituall and divine; ſo far as theſe can be brought under a rule: For we cannot preſume to preſcribe any rules to the Spirit in his motions, becauſe, as it is in the work of regeneration, ſo is it in the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of myſteries, the Spirit bloweth where, and when it pleaſeth; yet ſome rules may be given to the rationall faculty, which is ſubſervient unto the Spirit, by which, deceits may be prevented, and miſtakes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; that a ſpirituall man may be able to walk in the light, both by propoſing cautions to himſelf, and calling his thoughts unto an account, that he may diſcern his own ſpirit, and regulate his courſe ſo far as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth go, leſt he be led by ſome falſe light, and a deceived ſpirit bring him out of the way: For, when the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 1. 2. 3.</hi> doth warn every man not to think above that which he ought to think, but to think ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſobriety; as God hath diſtributed unto every one the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of faith, he doth cleerly give us a rule, by which we are to reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves in ſpirituall matters, to diſcern our own thoughts by a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the proportion which they have, with the Principle from which they flow: And as in this, ſo in all other acts of meditation, the rule will be found in the ſame kind of proportion.</p>
            <p>Now, the objects of meditation, concerning which doubts may ariſe, and wherein miſtakes may be incident, which by the regulating of our thoughts, may be prevented, or reſolved, are chiefly theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning the ſenſe of the Holy Scriptures, which are the dictates of the Holy Ghoſt: we finde that many doubts do ariſe in the minds of Interpreters, which without a certain rule, cannot be reſolved.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113716:25"/>
Therefore concerning Scripturall Interpretation, I conceive that the way of analyſing the Text literally, materially, and myſtically, may be delivered, ſo, as to diſcover the grounds of demonſtrating the true ſenſe thereof; ſo far as the proportion of faith doth lead us, and further we are not warranted to proceed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, concerning all other matters wherein the minde may be more free, and needs not be bound up (as in Scripturall meditation) to the dictates of anothers meaning; the rules are of two ſorts, ſome for Theoreticall, ſome for practicall meditations; and both theſe are either in humane or divine objects.</p>
            <p>The Theory of humane objects, may have rules to direct the mind to ſinde out hidden truths in naturall things.</p>
            <p>The Practicall meditations of humane matters require rules, diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wayes of prudency, by which the beſt courſe of doing lawfull buſineſſes may be found out and followed.</p>
            <p>The Theory of divine objects, muſt wholly be Scripturall; therefore all the rules which can be delivered to direct the mind to ſind out hidden truths of this kind, muſt be conſequences of that analyticall doctrine, which doth relate to the matters and myſteries of the Text.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the practicall meditations of the ſpirituall objects concern ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the doubts of conſcience, which Chriſtians may have within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or the works of edification to be intended towards others. Of the firſt rules may be given, how the conſcience ſhould reſolve it ſelf of its doubts; of the ſecond, how the works ſhould be proſecuted and propoſed toward others.</p>
            <p>Of all which, much is to be ſaid of very great concemment to the building up of our ſouls in truth and peace; but many outward lets and diſtractions, and ſome inward infirmities of mine own, take me off from the attention and intentiveneſſe which is requiſite in the elaborating of ſo weighty matters, time and leaſure is then requiſite; which I hope the Lord will grant, with other neceſſary graces: and this I am willing to aſſure you of; that you ſhall never be more willing to put me upon theſe tasks, then I ſhall be found (according to the ability which it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to grant unto me) ready and deſirous to apply my ſelf thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for your ediſication, as being in truth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate and faithfull ſervant in Chriſt,
J. Dury.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
